Harvard University. Corporation. Records of land and property owned by Harvard University, 1643-1835: an inventory
Records of land and property owned by Harvard University, 1643-1835
Harvard University Archives
UAI 15.750
Harvard University. Corporation.
6.46 cubic feet (11 document boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 9 oversize cabinet folders)
In the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, Harvard received numerous gifts of land and property from benevolent individuals as well as from the General Court of Massachusetts and the proprietors of several settlements in western Massachusetts. The Records of land and property owned by Harvard University contain records related to the land and property owned and managed by Harvard between 1643 and 1835 and include legal documents, leases and memoranda, surveyors' plans and appraisals of many of the properties, correspondence, bills, and other materials. Although management of the land holdings was largely the responsibility of the College Treasurer, these records demonstrate that Harvard's President and other staff were also actively involved in land-related concerns.
This document last updated 2011 January 31.
Acquisition information
The documents in this collection are University records and were acquired in the course of University business. Four of the documents were donated to the archives by Charles Holt Taylor in 1924 and 1931; this provenance information is noted at the item level in the following folder list.
Researcher Access
The Records of land and property owned by Harvard University are open for research. Pending conservation, materials in boxes 10, 11, 12, and 13 are closed to research due to their fragile state. These records have been severely damaged by mold, and some are so severely damaged that their contents are largely illegible (including all records related to Shawshin Farm in Billerica, Massachusetts). The contents of other damaged records are more clear and are listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
In the Harvard University Archives
Records of the Treasurer of Harvard University, 1669-2008
Records of the Harvard Corporation, 1650-1992
College Book 3 in Harvard University. Corporation. College Books, 1636-1827
Accounts of lands belonging to Harvard College, 1806 (UAI 15.798)
Publications of the Colonial Society of Massachusetts [transcriptions of documents in this collection, as well as engravings done after surveyors' plans in the collection, are found in multiple volumes of this publication]
Deed of sale for property in Framingham, Massachusetts, from Joseph Buckminster to Moses Haven, March 6, 1706 (HUM 34)
In the Massachusetts Archives
Eastern Lands Papers
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in twenty series, according to geographic location:
I. Rowley, 1643-1748
II. Pequot land, 1652-1674
III. Webb Estate (Boston), 1660-1827
IV. Pennoyer Estate, 1670-1829
V. Hayward's Pasture, 1672-1816
VI. Ward's Island (Bumpkin Island), 1680-1821
VII. Maine / "Eastern lands," 1690-1835
A. Merriconeag Neck, 1690-1729
B. Phillipsburg, 1727-1808
C. Bridgton, 1780-1807
D. Pownalborough, 1780-1833
E. Miscellaneous lands, 1785-1835
F. Lottery Lands, 1787-1835
G. Turner, 1787-1808
H. Fryeburg and Leeds / Livermore, 1796-1809
I. Bucksport, 1801-1835
J. Sullivan, 1802-1817
K. Correspondence with Prentiss Mellen, 1808-1827
L. Land Auction, 1832-1835
VIII. Newton, 1704-1812
IX. Rutland, 1718-1793
X. Framingham (Danforth Estate), 1698-1779
XI. Lunenburg, 1729-1756
XII. Narragansett farm, 1696-1829
XIII. Townsend, 1733-1802
XIV. Waltham Farm (Rogers Farm), 1737-1826
XV. Coggan's Marsh and Stoughton's Marsh, 1654/5-1823
XVI. Gridley Estate, 1761-1792
XVII. Winchendon, 1784-1808
XVIII. Stoughton's Pasture, 1786-1803
XIX. Granby, 1794-1798
XX. Other lands, 1647-1830
Records within each series are arranged chronologically, and undated records are located at the end of each series.
Scope and Content
The Records of land and property owned by Harvard University document the Harvard Corporation's management and oversight of the University's land and property holdings from the mid seventeenth century into the nineteenth century. These properties extended across New England, in what is now Connecticut, Rhode Island, Massachusetts, and Maine, and also included revenue generated from the lease of an estate in England. Records include correspondence; leases, bonds, deeds, wills, and other legal documents; surveyors' plans and assessments of various lands; bills; statements of account; and memoranda. The records provide insight into land settlement in colonial New England; the challenges of marking boundaries and establishing legal ownership of land; economic difficulties in the colonies; and the legal, interpersonal, and financial challenges of managing extensive property holdings. Many of the records were created by these Harvard Treasurers: Thomas Danforth, Thomas Brattle, John White, Edward Hutchinson, Thomas Hubbard, John Hancock, Ebenezer Storer, Jonathan Jackson, John Davis, Ebenezer Francis, and Thomas Wren Ward.
It should be noted that some documents whose dates are between January 1 and March 25 in the years prior to 1752 have been cited with the double date convention, e.g. February 27, 1658/9. This convention has been followed only when the document itself indicates the date in such a manner. This convention was used in England and the North American colonies between 1582 and 1752. The first date refers to the year according to the Julian calendar, which began on March 25, while the second refers to the year according to the Gregorian calendar, which began on January 1.
Series descriptions and folder list
- I. Rowley, 1643-1748, 1 document box (.45 cubic feet)
  Historical Note
  The Harvard-owned land in Rowley, Massachusetts was a bequest from Ezekiel Rogers (1590-1661), an English minister largely responsible for the settlement and incorporation of the town of Rowley in 1639. Rogers had served as minister of the Church at Rowley in Yorkshire (England) for almost two decades, but he was suspended from his duties there in 1638 because of increasing disagreement with the Church of England over religious doctrine. Rogers decided to flee to New England and, convincing twenty-two families among his congregation to accompany him, set sail on board the ship John of London in 1638. Also on board was the first printing press to arrive in America with several fonts of type, brought by the Reverend Joseph Glover (who died on the journey) and the printer Stephen Daye, accompanied by his sons, Stephen, Jr. and Matthew. The vessel arrived in Salem in December of 1638, and Rogers and his followers likely spent that winter in Salem. By the spring of 1639, they had settled in the town they would name Rowley (after the English village they had left behind); the town was incorporated on September 4, 1639. Rogers served as pastor there until his death on January 23, 1661.
  In his will, Rogers specified that "all [his] houses, barn, and orchard, and all [his] lands, pastures and commonages and meadows" (approximately 26 parcels of land, and 196 acres in total) should be given to the town and church of Rowley following his wife Mary's death, but with a requirement that would prove significant: the land would only belong to the town and church on the condition that neither of the two teaching elders' positions should remain vacant for longer than four years. Rogers specified that, should those posts remain vacant for more than four years, all the lands he had bequeathed should "be [instead given] to the use of Harvard College, at Cambridge, in New England." He also gave Harvard "all [his] Latin books [...] and some English books." By 1700, the church had allowed the elders' positions to remain vacant for too long, and the land was reverted to Harvard. Various legal investigations and agreements ensued, including a 1704 decision to lease the land, and a 1734 decision to sell the land off in lots. The College began to sell their portion of Rogers' property in 1735, and many Rowley inhabitants - including Nathaniel Bradstreet, Thomas Lambert, and Daniel Hale - were among the purchasers. By 1764 all of the land in Rowley belonging to Harvard had been sold.
  References
  Gage, Thomas. The History of Rowley, Anciently Including Bradford, Boxford, and Georgetown. Boston: Ferdinand Andrews, 1840.
  Jewett, Amos Everett and Emily Mabel Adams Jewett. Rowley, Massachusetts, ‘Mr. Ezechi Rogers Plantation,’ 1639-1850. Rowley: The Jewett Family of America, 1946.
  This series contains records related to the land and property in Rowley bequeathed to Harvard by Ezekiel Rogers, including documents created in the course of several legal disputes over ownership of the land and/or the right to access it. Many of the documents are manuscript copies of excerpts from the Rowley town records and appear to have been assembled for Harvard President Benjamin Wadsworth around 1736, as he was determining the best course of action in regards to the lands (presumably whether to continue leasing them, or to sell them). This series contains extracts of the wills of Thomas Barker, Joseph Jewett, Ezekiel Rogers, and Mary Rogers; legal agreements related to the division of the so-called "warehouse pasture"; a plan of the Rowley lands; leases (from the period that Harvard rented out the property); records of legal disputes over land ownership; committee reports; a surveyor's report; and depositions about trespassers, in addition to other documents.
  - Manuscript extract from Rowley town records concerning sale of “warehouse pasture” to Thomas Barker on Nov. 10, 1643, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 1
    Note on verso indicates that this document was consulted by Benjamin Wadsworth on Sept. 24, 1736.
  - Manuscript extracts from Rowley birth, death, and marriage records, 1650-1693, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 2
  - Will of Thomas Barker, 1651, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 3
  - Will of Thomas Barker, 1651 (second manuscript copy), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 4
    Signed by Thomas Barker in the presence of Ezekiel Rogers, Thomas Mighill, and Matthew Boyes. “Proved” in Ipswich court Jan. 25, 1651 by the oath of Thomas Mighill and Matthew Boyes and signed by Robert Lord, clerk. Note on verso: “Compared by ye President Collson Sept. 24, 1736.”
  - Manuscript copy of Joseph Jewett’s will, Feb. 15, 1660, copied ca. 1661?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 5
  - Manuscript copy of Ezekiel Rogers' will, April 17, 1660, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 6
    Rogers' will includes an autobiographical passage, as well as rants against the Anabaptists, the Antimonians, and those who wear their hair in “that generall disguisement of long Russian-like hair.” Witnessed by Samuell Brocklobanke, Maximillien Jewett, and John Brocklobanke.
  - Extracts from Rowley town records regarding the dates of death of Ezekiel Rogers and Mary Rogers and the borders of an ox pasture, 1660-1678, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 7
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records regarding land, 1661 and 1681, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 8
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records regarding Ezekiel Rogers’ will, April 13, 1664, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 9
    Includes addenda that appear to date from 1664 and 1729.
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records regarding Ezekiel Rogers’ will and Rowley lands, April 13, 1664, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 10
    Attested by five men on May 5, 1664.
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records regarding Ezekiel Rogers’ will and Rowley lands, April 13, 1664, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 11
    Note on verso indicates that document was consulted by Harvard’s president Benjamin Wadsworth on Sept. 24, 1736.
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records related to allotment of land on Hog Island (now Choate Island), 1666, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 12
  - Manuscript copies of will of Mary Rogers, April 28, 1669, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folders 13 and 14
    Authenticated on Nov. 2, 1670 by Samuel Symons. Original was signed by Thomas Spoford, Timothy Palmmer, and Faith Swan.
  - Manuscript excerpt from town records regarding fences on Rowley lands, March 4, 1672(?), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 15
  - Manuscript excerpt from Rowley town records regarding land, Jan. 1, 1677, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 16
  - Extract of writ concerning legal case of Harvard College vs. Judah Clark, for trespassing on Rowley lands, Jan. 1, 1677 (?), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 17
  - Manuscript excerpt from Rowley town records regarding land, Jan. 22, 1677, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 18
  - Manuscript copy of revised will of Mary Rogers, July 22, 1678, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 19
    Rogers willed her sheep, cows, bees, pewter, silver, a looking glass, “a little Bellmette pott,” and many other items. Authenticated in Ipswich court on April 1, 1679
  - Legal document concerning ownership of “warehouse pasture,” July 23, 1678, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 20
  - Manuscript excerpts of Rowley town records, 1693-1701, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 21
    Contains excerpts from meetings held March 23, 1693; March 4, 1694/5; Dec. 28, 1698; and April 14, 1701.
  - Manuscript extracts from Rowley town records, ca. 1700, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 22
  - Legal agreement to divide “warehouse pasture” in Rowley between Ezekiel Northend and Harvard College, April 5, 1704, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 23
    The agreement was between Ezekiel Northend and Philip Fowler, who served as attorney for Thomas Brattle, Treasurer of Harvard College. They agreed to divide the pasture, which had formerly belonged to Ezekiel Rogers and Ezekiel Northend (both deceased). Northend had left his share to his son, and Rogers had given his to Harvard. Signed by Daniel Ring, (?) Perkins, Philip Fowler and Ezekiel Northend. Certified April 18, 1704 by Stephen Sewall.
  - Manuscript copy of minutes from Rowley town meetings, April 14, 1701 and May 25, 1704, including vote against trespassers on Rowley lands, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 24
    Lists the names of those who dissented in the vote about trespassers.
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records, 1643-1704, related to legal case of Harvard College vs. Lambert, compiled ca. 1704?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 25
  - Manuscript excerpts of Harvard Treasurer Thomas Brattle’s entries related to Rowley lands, 1701-1712, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 26
  - Account of rents for Rowley lands in 1716, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 27
    Lists the names of the renters.
  - Account of rents for Rowley lands in 1717, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 28
  - Account of rents for Rowley lands in 1718, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 29
  - Account of rents for Rowley lands in 1719, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 30
  - Account of rents for Rowley lands in 1720, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 31
  - Manuscript excerpts from Harvard Treasurer Thomas Brattle’s “book,” concerning Ezekiel Rogers’ land in Rowley, 1700-1704, 1710, compiled ca. 1722?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 32
  - Statement of Thomas Berry’s account with Harvard College, 1723-1726, includes statement of account with “Woods Hibberts,” 1724, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 33
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records related to Ezekiel Rogers’ land holdings, 1643 and 1677, compiled for Benjamin Wadsworth Aug. 1, 1726, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 34
    Contains lengthy excerpts from the town records; also includes a letter from Rowley’s town clerk, Thomas Lambert, to Mr. (Nicholas?) Sever.
  - Report of Harvard committee on Rowley lands, Oct. 24, 1726, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 35
  - Memorandum about Rowley lands, Nov. 14, 1726, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 36
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records related to various plots of land, 1677 and 1680, compiled for Harvard on Dec. 7, 1726, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 37
  - Note from Rev. T. (Thomas?) Prince regarding Ezekiel Rogers and his assistants, ca. 1729, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 38
    Note refers to a June 3, 1729 letter, so its date is presumably soon after.
  - Minutes from meeting of freeholders in Rowley regarding land and fences, Sept. 18, 1730, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 39
  - Benjamin Wadsworth’s account of Benjamin Smith’s statement regarding Rowley lands, Dec. 22, 1731, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 40
  - Account of Rowley lands given by Ezekiel Rogers, March 18, 1731/2, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 41
  - Plan of a piece of land in Rowley belonging to Harvard, ca. 1732?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 42
    Undated, but found with other materials from 1732.
  - Statement concerning sale of lands in Rowley, Feb. 15, 1733, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 43
  - Manuscript copy of vote to address General Court for leave to sell Rowley lands, and statement from Mr. Smith of Rowley, April 5, 1733, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 44
  - Lease of land in Rowley to Benjamin Smith, April 5, 1733, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 45
  - Minutes from meeting of Rowley inhabitants concerning sale of college lands, Jan. 9, 1733/4, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 46
  - Letter from Jedidiah Jewet to Edward Hutchinson, Jan. 26, 1733/4, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 47
    Jedidiah Jewet, pastor of the First Church of Rowley, explains in this letter that his congregation does not object to Harvard’s selling land in Rowley.
  - Manuscript copy of vote appointing committee to visit and survey college lands at Rowley, April 14, 1735, and portion of June 2 (1735?) vote, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 48
  - Report of Harvard’s committee for Rowley lands, Aug. 18, 1735, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 49
    The committee advised selling the Rowley lands. Signed by Edward Hutchinson, Henry Flynt, Nathaniel Appleton, and Andrew Bordman.
  - Report of Harvard’s committee for Rowley lands, Aug. 18, 1735 (second copy), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 50
    Signed by Henry Flynt.
  - Manuscript copy of letter to Thomas Lambert, town clerk of Rowley, Sept. 10, 1735, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 51
    The author of the letter is unclear, although it clearly originated at Harvard.
  - Decisions by First Church of Rowley and Town of Rowley to appoint committees to settle disputes over land bequeathed by Ezekiel Rogers, Oct. 23, 1735, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 52
  - Report of Jonathan Wade’s survey of Rowley lands, Dec. 23, 1735, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 53
  - Draft of articles of agreement regarding division of Rowley lands, 1735, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 54
  - List of concerns and discrepancies regarding Harvard’s interests in Rowley lands, 1735, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 55
  - Draft of deed to be used in sale of College lands in Rowley, ca. 1735?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 56
  - Benjamin Wadsworth’s delegation of power of attorney to William Brattle, Feb. 12, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 57
    Signed by Benjamin Wadsworth, John Eliot, and Abigail Parrott.
  - Deposition of John Davis regarding the “warehouse pasture,” Feb. 12, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 58
  - Deposition of Joseph Pearson regarding the “warehouse pasture,” Feb. 15, 1736 (2 copies), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 59
  - Deposition of Moses Platts regarding the “warehouse pasture,” Feb. 15, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 60
  - Manuscript copy of writ regarding legal case involving Nathaniel Bradstreet, Thomas Lambert, Joseph Varnom, Jane Varnom (and others?), Sept. 8, 1736 (2 copies), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 61
  - Manuscript copy of Harvard Corporation vote concerning Lambert vs. Bradstreet / “warehouse pasture,” Oct. 11, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 62
  - List of needed documents regarding Rowley lands, Nov. 2, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 63
  - Deposition of James Platts regarding the “warehouse pasture,” Dec. 17, 1736 (2 copies), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 64
    Platts claimed to have seen both “the wife of Thomas Wood” and “Mr. Payson’s negro” driving cattle by his house and then grazing them in the so-called warehouse pasture.
  - Harvard College claim to “warehouse pasture” in Rowley, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 65
  - Continuance of legal case, Thomas Lambert vs. Nathaniel Bradstreet, 1736, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 66
  - Notes on chronology of land transfers and disputes in Rowley, ca. 1736?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 67
  - Statement concerning legal case, Lambert vs. Harvard College, April 21, 1737, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 68
  - Manuscript copy of Moses Bradstreet’s deposition regarding “warehouse pasture,” Nov. 7, 1737 (2 copies), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 69
  - Essex Superior Court judgment in Lambert vs. Harvard College, Nov. 1737, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 70
    The judge for the case was William Brattle; he found in favor of Harvard.
  - Prices set for Rowley lands, ca. 1737?, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 71
    Date is an estimate based on when the land was about to be sold.
  - Edward Holyoke’s delegation of power of attorney to John Read and Edmund Goffe, May 6, 1738, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 72
  - Manuscript copy of writ of review for legal case, Lambert vs. Harvard College, April 7, 1739, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 73
  - Manuscript copy of Massachusetts House of Representatives vote, Nov. 23, 1748 (2 copies), UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 74
  - List of lands in Rowley belonging to Harvard College, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 75
  - List of lands in Rowley already measured or to be measured, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 76
  - Memorandum concerning “Mr. Reed’s advice” and need for proof of Ezekiel Rogers’ gift of Rowley lands, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 77
  - Manuscript excerpt of Rowley town records concerning land owned by Ezekiel Rogers, Thomas Lambert, and others, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 78
  - Memorandum regarding Ezekiel Rogers’ land in Rowley, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 79
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 80
  - Memorandum regarding College lands in Rowley, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 81
  - Minutes regarding College lands in Rowley, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 82
  - Memoranda regarding College lands in Rowley, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 83
  - List of lots “drawn by Thomas Wood George Hibert for Harvard,” undated, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 84
  - Manuscript excerpts from Rowley town records, dates illegible, UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folder 85
- II. Pequot land, 1652-1674, .07 cubic feet (7 folders)
  The records in this series are related to land which formerly belonged to the Pequot tribe of Native Americans (located in what is now Connecticut and Rhode Island) which was granted to Harvard College by the General Court in the 1650s. A first tract of land, allocated on October 19, 1652, comprised 200 acres and a second, allocated on May 18, 1653, comprised 800 acres. These two grants were rendered null by a third allocation, made on May 19, 1658, which comprised “2,100 acres in Pequot Country.” Thomas Danforth, the Harvard Treasurer who was apparently responsible for negotiating these grants of land, was also awarded 300 acres of Pequot lands for his efforts.
  This series contains manuscript copies of court decisions related to the land grants, including records related to disputes over whether or not the land in question was in the Massachusetts Bay Colony or the Connecticut Colony, and which colony had the right to allocate the land. Also included is a copy of the General Court's allocation of Pequot land to George Dennison and a copy of the court's decision to fine two men for trespassing on the College's Pequot lands. These records do not reveal the ultimate disposition of the Pequot lands belonging to Harvard, although Josiah Quincy wrote in The History of Harvard University that "the College obtained nothing by this gift."
  - Manuscript copies of court decisions related to allocation of lands to Harvard College, Oct. 19, 1652; May 18, 1653; and May 19, 1658, UAI 15.750 Box 1, Folder 1